A Guide to the Virginia Auditor of Public Accounts - George Rogers Clark Papers, Western Expedition Quartermaster Records, 1779-1784
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Virginia Auditor of Public Accounts - George Rogers Clark Papers, Western Expedition Quartermaster Records, 1779-1784
The Library of Virginia
APA 205
1 cu. ft. (3 boxes)
Virginia Auditor of Public Accounts
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Transferred from the Auditor of Public Accounts in 1913.
Biographical Information
George Rogers Clark was born 19 November 1752 in Albemarle County, Virginia, to John Clark (1725-1799) and Ann Rogers Clark (1728-1798). Clark learned surveying from his grandfather in Caroline County, Virginia. He explored down the Ohio and Kanawha Rivers in what is now Kentucky and West Virginia and surveyed farms for settlers arriving in that territory. Clark served as a captain in the Virginia militia during Lord Dunmore's War in 1774, and the next year returned to Kentucky to survey lands for the Ohio Company. When the Revolution began, Clark encouraged Virginia to protect Kentucky from the British and Native Americans. He captured Kaskaskia, Illinois, from the British 4 July 1778 and won the allegiance of French settlers in Vincennes, Indiana. When the British took Vincennes in October 1778, Clark recaptured it 25 February 1779. He was responsible for the defense of the Northwest Territory during the rest of the American Revolution. After Kentucky troops were defeated at Blue Licks, Kentucky, by the Shawnee 19 August 1782, Clark retaliated with an attack on Chillicothe, Ohio, defeating the Shawnee 4 November 1782. After the American Revolution ended, Clark served on the Board of Commissioners which allotted the lands in Kentucky and the Northwest Territory granted by Virginia to its soldiers. He left Kentucky to live on the Indiana frontier but was never fully reimbursed by Virginia for his wartime expenditures. He spent the final decades of his life evading creditors and living in increasing poverty and obscurity. Clark lived the last few years of his life with his sister and her husband outside Louisville, Kentucky, where he died 13 February 1818.
Scope and Content
This is an artificial collection of records concerning George Rogers Clark and the conquest of the Old Northwest during and after the revolutionary war. The records, which are now so intermingled they defy any attempt to separate them, were brought together from two distinct sets of records. The first set contained Clark's original accounts and vouchers, which had been submitted to the auditors of public accounts for settlement in 1779. These records were misplaced by the auditors and when the Board of Western Commissioners sought to settle his accounts in 1783, Clark produced a second set of records consisting of copies of the materials submitted in 1779, in addition to the records he had created since then. The Clark papers, then, consist of the misplaced records (since found) submitted to the auditor, as well as the vouchers submitted to the Board of Western Commissioners.
The collection is listed in chronological order in the finding aid, although the materials were arranged physically by size into different size boxes. Researchers should pay special attention to note the box and folder numbers.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged chronologically.
Contents List
- Expense accounts, 1778 March - 1779 October. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Also contains: An invoice of sundry merchandise received out of the county store at St. Louis and sundry items for the use of the Troops under the command of Col. Gorge Rogers Clark; and an Inventory of merchandise remaining in store at Fort Clarke the 12th April 1779 and then delivered to William Shannon, Esquire Conductor General.
- Ledger, 1778 March 30- 1781 October 1. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  The State of Virginia to Brigadier General G.R. Clark, for sundry payments, expenses and other disbursements by him made in behalf of the said state and Illinois Department.
- Abstract of Ledger, 1778 March 30- 1781 October 1. (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Account book, 1778 September 9 - 1779 September 13. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Abstract of ammunition and provisions issued to the militia in actual service at the Falls of Ohio by Jacob Pyeatt.
- Account book [No. 1], 1778 December 15 - 1782 July 19. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Col. John Montgomery and others with Commonwealth of Virginia accounts.
- Ledger, 1778 December 16 - 1784 July 10. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Account of money advanced sundry persons in the Illinois Department.
- Account book, 1779 March 6 - July 31. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Account of provisions issued to the troops at Fort Patrick Henry by William Bingeman, D.C.I. [D.C. Issues]. Also includes copy of a letter, 8 March 1779, from William Shannon to Adam Bingeman, regarding the amount of rations to be issued at the different posts.
- William Shannon's order and letter book [No. 1 D], 1779 March 6 - 1783 March 14. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  Contains copies or Clark's orders and letters written to various recipients including: John Bowman, George R. Clark, Henry Croucher, John Floyd, Patrick Kennedy, J.M.P. LeGras, Joseph Lindsay, John Montgomery, William Peyton, George Slaughter, John Todd, George Wilson, and James Wright.
- Ledger, 1779 March 17 - 1782 April 29. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  The Commonwealth of Virginia in account with William Shannon.
- Ledger, 1779 March 19 - August 20. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  Ledger of Isaac Bowman, Quartermaster. Account of sales of goods at the Plunder Store after the taking of Fort St. Vincent's, Western Country. Includes an index.
- Account book [No. 3 B], 1779 April 1 - July 31. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  Account of provisions issued to the troops at Fort Clark and elsewhere in the Illinois Country by John Marney, D.C. of Issues. Also includes copy of a letter, 1 April 1779, from William Shannon, Esquire Conductor General, to John Marney, D.C. of Issues, regarding the amount of rations to be issued at the different posts.
- Account, 1779 June 1 - October 11. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  An account of quartermaster stores issued in the Illinois and its dependencies by John Reid, quartermaster of the Illinois Regiment.
- Account book, 1779 June 23 - 1781 May 24. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  Abstract of provisions received and issued to the troops in the Illinois under the command of Col. George R. Clark by Henry Croucher, D.C., as per his papers left with Patrick Kennedy, Assistant Conductor [1779 June 23 - August 31]; and Account of provisions purchased, received, and issued in the Illinois under the direction of Patrick Kennedy, Deputy Conductor to the troops under the command of Colonel George Rogers Clark [1779 Sept. 1 - 1781 May 24]. Also includes copy of the letter, 23 June 1779, from Capt. William Shannon Conductor General, to Henry Croucher, D.C., at Kaskaskais, regarding rations allowed.
- Account book [No. 7], 1779 June 24 - 1780 June 12. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  A list of fournitures, ligaments, and medicines, which I have made and furnished to the Regiment of the Illinois under the command of Colonel Clark and Mr. Montgomery Lt. Colonel [from Dr. Francis Conard]. At the end of the account is a note from Lt. Col. John Montgomery certifying that he believed Doctor Conard furnished the medicine but that he thought the doctor's medicines were high-priced.
- Account book [No. 4 D], 1779 August 1 - October 20. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  Account of provisions issued to the troops at Fort Patrick Henry by Zephaniah Blackford, D.C. of Issues. Also includes copy of the letter, 1 August 1779, from William Shannon, Esquire Condoctor General, to Zephaniah Blackford, D.C. of Issues, regarding the amount of rations to be issued at the different posts.
- Account book and journal, 1779 November 15 - 1780 February 10. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  Account book and journal of John Todd detailing a trip from Kaskaskia to the Falls of Ohio.
- Account book, 1780 January 1 - 1781 December 15. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  Abstract of disbursements in the Quartermasters Department by Bland Ballard, Q.M., under the direction of Col. George Slaughter at Fort Nelson.
- Account book [No. 6 A], 1780 January - 1781 December. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Abstract of provision issued at Fort Nelson by Bland Ballard, Commissary person under the direction of Col. George Slaughter, Commandant. Also includes return of powder, ammunition, tobacco, and forage issued.
- Account book [No. 1 E], 1780 April - 1781 October. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  Martin Coney's account of issues of ammunition, arms, etc., at Fort Jefferson and the Falls of the Ohio.
- Account book, 1780 June - 1781 January. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  Account book of provisions issued at Fort Jefferson by John Dodge. Also includes copies of letters, 1779-1780, between John Dodge and John Todd, George Clark, and John Montgomery.
- Affidavit of John South, Sr., and John South, 1780 July 12. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  Affidavit appraising the value of horses.
- Account book [No. 1 C], 1780 July 12 - August 31. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  An account of provisions issued to the troops commanded by Col. G.R. Clark on the expedition against the Shawanese, by Thomas Vickroy, D.C. of Issue. Includes an extract of instructions from Capt. William Shannon, 10 July 1780, appointing Thomas Vickroy Deputy Commander of Issues and instructing him on rations to issue.
- Voucher books, 1781 March - June. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  Issued by Robert Wickliff [3 volumes].
- Receipt book, 1781 April - June. (Box 2, Folder 14)
  Receipt book of Thomas Gist.
- Account book [No. 1 F], 1781 May - October. (Box 2, Folder 15)
  Account book listing supplies issued by Martin Carney.
- Account book [No. 1 G], 1781 July - October. (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Ledger, 1781 June - 1783 February. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  George Walls Quartermaster's book.
- Accounts, 1781 July - September. (Box 2, Folder 17)
  Account of rum issued.
- Account book, 1781 July - 1784 April. (Box 2, Folder 18)
  Account book of forage received and issued by Major George Walls, Quartermaster General Western Expedition.
- Receipt book, 1781 July 18 - December 8. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  Receipt book of Quartermaster General, Western Expedition.
- Receipt book, 1781 July 29 - November 27. (Box 4, Folder 2)
- ,.
- ,.
- ,.
- ,.
- ,.
- ,.
- ,.
- ,.
- ,.
- ,.
- ,.
- ,.
- ,.
- ,.
- ,.
- ,.
- ,.